Guide to the Arthur William Galston Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Arthur William Galston papers
1938-2007
MS 1712
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
25.75
(28 boxes)
The papers include correspondence, course materials, writings, and photographs documenting Arthur William Galston's career as a plant physiologist and a professor at Yale University. The papers highlight Galston's concern over the ecological harm done by herbicides and his efforts to end the use of Agent Orange, which was sprayed as a defoliant in Vietnam by the United States military. The papers also document Galston's visit to the People's Republic of China in 1971.
Galston, Arthur W. (Arthur William), 1920-2008
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Arthur W. Galston, 1996 and 2002. Gift of Beth Galston and William Galston, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
As established by Yale Corporation regulations, box 19 of the original accession is restricted until January 1, 2047.
Accession 2009-M-022 is restricted until January 1, 2042. A review of the materials in this accession for student records requiring additional restriction must occur before this accession can be opened for research. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
Biographical / Historical
Arthur William Galston was born on April 21, 1920. He received a Ph.D. from the University of Illinois in 1943 and joined the Yale University faculty as an instructor in botany in 1946. From 1951 to 1955 Galston was an associate professor of biology at California Institute of Technology, following which he returned to Yale. He served as chairman of the botany department (1961-1962), director of the division of biological sciences (1965-1966), and chairman of the biology department (1985-1988). In 1971 Galston became the first American scientist to visit the People's Republic of China. He was named professor emeritus in 1990. Arthur Galston died on June 15, 2008, in Hamden, Connecticut.
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence, course materials, writings, and photographs documenting Arthur William Galston's career as a plant physiologist and a professor at Yale University. The papers highlight Galston's concern over the ecological harm done by herbicides and his efforts to end the use of Agent Orange, which was sprayed as a defoliant in Vietnam by the United States military. The papers also document Galston's visit to the People's Republic of China in 1971.
Acupuncture; Agent Orange; Botany -- Study and teaching; Defoliants -- War use; Ecology; Environmental protection; Herbicides -- War use; Plant physiology; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Chemical warfare; China -- Description and travel; Galston, Arthur W. (Arthur William), 1920-2008; Westing, Arthur H.; Scientists' Institute for Public Information; Yale University -- Faculty
- Original accession, Accession 1997-M-031
  - Speeches, writings, Circa 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - General files
    - 1958-1960
      - I-K (Box 1)
      - K, O-Z (Box 2)
    - 1955-1958
      - A-J (Box 2)
      - K-P (Box 3)
    - 1961-1964
      - A-G (Box 3)
      - H-P (Box 4)
  - Yale materials
    General
    See also: Yale materials restricted, Box 19.
    - Departmental papers, Circa 1952-1959 (Box 4)
    - Course notes, Circa 1959-1971 (Box 5)
    - Administrative files, Circa 1959-1971 (Box 5)
    - Course materials, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous and personal papers, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Herbicide use in Vietnam, Circa 1971 (Box 6)
    Scope and Contents
    Comprises mostly printed material, including testimony before the Senate.
  - Herbicide use in Vietnam, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Memorabilia, including notes for studying Russian language, n.d. (Box 7)
  - General files
    - 1978-1979
      - A-T (Box 8)
      - Freedom of Information Privacy Act (Box 8)
      - Natural history (Box 8)
      - Scientists' Institute for Public Information (SIPI) [Dr. Hieu's visit] (Box 8)
      - Timothy Dwight College (Box 8)
      - Ton That Tung visit (Box 8)
      - U-W (Box 8)
      - Westing, Arthur (Box 8)
      - Y-Z (Box 8)
    - 1979-1980
      - B (Box 8)
      - Botanical Congress (Box 8)
      - C-D (Box 8)
      - Darwin Symposium (Box 8)
      - E-F (Box 8)
      - Freedom of Information Privacy Branch (Box 8)
      - G-N (Box 8)
      - Natural history (Box 8)
      - 0-P (Box 8)
      - PROPHET computer system (Box 8)
      - Q-R (Box 8)
      - Reviews (Box 8)
      - S (Box 8)
      - SIPI (Box 9)
      - Skoog meeting (Box 9)
      - T (Box 9)
      - Timothy Dwight (Box 9)
      - U-W (Box 9)
      - Westing, Arthur (Box 9)
      - X-Z (Box 9)
  - Central Mechanism in Plant Development, 1976 (Box 9)
  - SIPI, 1977-1979 (Box 9)
  - Anaximandrian Society, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 9)
  - General files
    - 1981-1982
      - A-B (Box 9)
      - Berzelius (Box 9)
      - Brailovsky (Box 9)
      - C-N (Box 9)
      - NASA-space platform (Box 9)
      - O-P (Box 9)
      - PROPHET computer system (Box 9)
      - Provost (Box 9)
      - Pugwash (Box 9)
      - Q (Box 9)
      - Reviews (Box 9)
      - R-W (Box 9)
      - Wareing (Box 9)
      - Westing, Arthur (Box 9)
      - Y (Box 9)
      - Yale University. Department of Biology (Box 10)
    - 1982-1983
      - A-D (Box 10)
      - Dwyer (Box 10)
      - E-H (Box 10)
      - Hesse (Box 10)
      - I-M (Box 10)
      - McKnight (Box 10)
      - N (Box 10)
      - Noland (Box 10)
      - O-P (Box 10)
      - Pugwash (Box 10)
      - Q-R (Box 10)
      - Racusen and Galston (Box 10)
      - Review (Box 10)
      - S-W (Box 10)
      - Wareing (Box 10)
      - Westing, Arthur (Box 10)
      - Y (Box 10)
      - NASA Space Shuttle Report (Box 10)
      - NASA--Life Science Advisory Committee (LSAC) (Box 10)
      - New York State (Box 10)
      - Pesticide biochemistry and physiology (Box 10)
      - Plant growth regulation (Box 10)
      - Scandinavian Society for Plant Physiology (Box 10)
      - Scientist's Committee on Chemical and Biological Warfare (Box 10)
      - Scientist's Institute for Public Information (Box 10)
      - Cooperman (Box 10)
      - U.S. Committee for Scientific Cooperation with Vietnam (Box 10)
  - Galston experiments, 1960 (Box 11)
  - Student materials from Cornell and University of Illinois
    - Biophysics (Pollard), 1946 (Box 11)
    - Plant chemistry, 1943 (Box 11)
    - Chemistry and botany notebooks, 1938-1949 (Box 11)
  - Various materials on herbicide and defoliant use in Vietnam, 1968-1983 (Box 12)
    - Articles (Box 12)
    - Journals (Box 12)
    - Scientific reports and essays (Box 12)
  - Oversize (items previously in box 12)
    - Dedication programs and articles
      - Josiah Willard Gibbs Research Laboratories, 1955 October 28 (Box 12A)
      - Kline Biology Tower, 1966 October 28 (Box 12A)
    - Diploma, merit certificate, Navy discharge papers, 1953, 1955, undated (Box 12A)
    - Graphs, annotated, "frozen buds", 1981 (Box 12A)
    - "Humerus Picture", Undated (Box 12A)
      Cartoon-like rendering of the humerus bone.
    - Photographs of Galston, Circa 1950, undated (Box 12A)
  - Additional materials on herbicide use, 1970-1981
    - Arizona
      - 1956-1979 (Box 13)
      - 1979-1980 (Box 13)
    - Environmental Protection Agency, (EPA) (Box 13)
    - Halifax (Box 13)
    - Kellner Canyon-Russel Gulch, Arizona (Box 13)
  - Materials on 2, 4, 5-T and Silvex
    - Environmental Protection Agency (Box 14)
    - Direct testimony of Dr. Galston (Box 14)
  - New York Times, 1971 (Box 14)
  - China, 1971 (Box 14)
  - China diary (Box 14)
  - China letters, 1971-1972
    - A-F (Box 14)
    - G-L (Box 14)
    - Official (Box 14)
    - M-S (Box 14)
    - Singer (Box 14)
    - Singer: Science for the People (Box 14)
    - T-Z (Box 14)
    - Tannebaum (Box 14)
  - Acupuncture
    - A-F (Box 14)
    - G-L (Box 14)
    - M-R (Box 14)
    - S-Z (Box 14)
  - Chinese applicants
    - A-F (Box 14)
    - G-L (Box 14)
    - M-R (Box 14)
    - S-Z (Box 14)
  - International Commission of Enquiry into U.S. crimes in Indochina, 1972 (Box 14)
  - Medical aid to Indochina, Inc., 1972-1973 (Box 14)
  - Prospective visits--Federation of American Scientists (FAS) (Box 14)
  - Clippings [Dr. Galston and Singer] (Box 14)
  - China and Vietnam
    - Invitations, 1971-1972
      - Writing (Box 15)
      - Speaking (Box 15)
    - China science notes, 1971-1973 (Box 15)
    - Vietnam notes, 1972
      - Signer (Box 15)
      - Galston (Box 15)
      - Vietnam trip (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 15)
    - Democratic Republic of Vietnam, 1971-1976
      - Notes (Box 15)
      - Trip
        - SIPI releases (Box 15)
        - United Press International photos (Box 15)
      - Writings (Box 15)
    - United Press International (UPI), 1975 (Box 15)
    - Register (Box 15)
    - Boston Globe (Box 15)
    - China book, 1972 (Box 15)
    - Acupuncture articles (Box 15)
    - Photos (Box 15)
    - Information, 1968-1972
      - Vietnam (Box 15)
      - Sussex (Box 15)
    - Galston statements (Box 15)
  - General correspondence, 1969-1974
    - A-L (Box 16)
    - M-Z (Box 16)
    - Herbicides and Vietnam (Box 16)
    - Leitenberg, Milton (Box 16)
    - Meselson, Matthew (Box 16)
    - Neilands, J. B. (Box 16)
    - Westing, Arthur H. (Box 16)
    - Zablocki (Box 16)
  - Clippings
    - Arthur William Galston (Box 16)
    - Dow Chemical Company (Box 16)
    - Newspapers (Box 16)
  - Reports, 1968-1976
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) (Box 16)
    - Environmental Protection Agency (Box 16)
    - Defoliation
      - Fred H. Tschirley (Box 16)
      - Thomas Whiteside (Box 16)
    - Dioxins (Box 16)
    - Herbicide Assessment Committee (Box 16)
    - Midwest Research Institute (MRI) (Box 16)
    - Toxins (Box 16)
    - 2, 4-D toxicity (Box 16)
  - Conferences, 1968-1974
    - Dallas (Box 16)
    - Stockholm (Box 16)
  - Government, 1966-1969 (Box 16)
  - Koch-McCarthy (Box 16)
  - Congressional bills and records (Box 17)
  - Senator Nelson (Box 17)
  - Nixon statement (Box 17)
  - Yale University
    - Reports (Box 17)
    - "Day of Reflection", 1969 March 4 (Box 17)
  - Articles, 1967-1970
    - Scientist and Citizen (Box 17)
    - "Coastal Conservation," J.P. Milton (Box 17)
    - Pfeiffer et al. (Box 17)
    - Minarik, Charles E. (Box 17)
    - Westing, Arthur H. (Box 17)
  - Newsletters (Box 17)
  - Herbicides, 1966-1970
    - Cook (Box 17)
    - Mark, Richard E. (Box 17)
    - Meselson, Matthew (Box 17)
    - Mikva (Box 17)
    - Minarik and Fort Detrick (Box 17)
    - Neilands, J.B. (Box 17)
    - Williams, Hill (Box 17)
  - Arsenic (Box 17)
  - Pesticides (Box 17)
  - British clippings (Box 17)
  - Bratislavia paper (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous articles and reports (Box 17)
  - Trips, 1986
    - China (Box 18)
    - Budapest (Box 18)
  - Botany reports (Box 18)
  - Herbicide use in Vietnam, Circa 1983 (Box 18)
    Includes correspondence, writings, reports, and symposia notes.
  - Yale materials restricted, Circa 1952-1971 (Box 19, Folder 1-39)
    Consists of graduate student and personnel files.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Student and personnel files are restricted until January 1, 2047 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
- Additional Material, 1970-1985; Accession 2003-M-013
  - Correspondence with George Pierson and John Muyskens concerning Yale admissions, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - List of Galston's writings relating to science and public policy, Circa 1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, 1933-2007; Accession 2009-M-022
  Access to this entire accession is closed until January 1, 2042, because of the presence of restricted Yale materials throughout. Beyond the Yale restriction, a review of the materials in this accession for student records, which are scattered throughout the accession and require additional restriction, must occur before this accession can be opened for research.
  This accession contains correspondence, presentations, files related to various aspects of Galston's service and teaching at Yale, and topical and research files. Unless otherwise noted, descriptions in the inventory are of single folders.
  - General files
    Includes correspondence and related materials.
    - A-R, Circa 1947-1990; 41 (Box 1)
    - S-Z and e-mail, Circa 1947-1999; 17 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and related materials filed by name of individual, 1947-2003; 12 (Box 2)
    Callahan, Cullman, Giamatti, Kankel, Levin, Needham, Sawhney, Schmidt, Schwartz, Siegel, Siu, and Tippo
  - Yale materials
    - Bioethics course materials, 1991-2003; 14 (Box 2)
    - Yale course materials, including bioethics, aging, human genome, and agricutlural genetics, Circa 1946-2004; 9 (Box 2)
    - Yale course materials, including bioethics, aging, human genome, and agricultural genetics, Circa 1989-2006; 17 (Box 3)
    - Yale University, Interdisciplinary Bioethics Committee and Project, 1989-2004; 5 (Box 3)
    - Yale University, Interdisciplinary Center for Bioethics, executive committee meeting agendas, minutes, and related materials, 2005-2007; 3 (Box 6)
    - Yale University, Interdisciplinary Center for Bioethics, executive committee meeting agendas, minutes, and related materials, 2005-2007; 2 (Box 7)
    - Yale University, Bioethics and Public Policy lecture series, correspondence and related materials, 1994-2004; 3 (Box 7)
    - Yale Department of Biology materials, Circa 1967-2007; 14 (Box 3)
      Includes financial materials, faculty meetings, correspondence, grant proposals, departmental seminars, and materials on the Galston Prize in Plant Biology.
    - Yale College and University materials, Circa 1986-1995; 4 (Box 3)
    - Biographical materials, including vita and retirment files, Circa 1980-2002; 7 (Box 3)
    - Yale student complaint regarding Biblical references in class, correspondence and essay, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Student materials from Galston's undergraduate and graduate years, 1933-1942; 15 (Box 4)
    Includes notes, handouts, exams, and printed ephemera.
  - Reviews and other writings, 1987-2004; 3 (Box 4)
  - Notes, transparencies, and other lecture materials, 1978-2004; 8 (Box 4)
  - Topical files
    - Griswold/Brewster Presidential Papers Project, 1990-1993 (Box 4)
    - Michael Evenari biography materials, 1986 (Box 4)
    - Cal Tech Division of Biology materials, including staff meeting minutes, 1947-1954 (Box 4)
    - Hebrew University honorary degree correspondence, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Joyce Foundation grant materials, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Life of the Green Planet revision, 2003-2007 (Box 5)
    - Wye photograph and correspondence, 2003 (Box 5)
    - Green wisdom/Plants are smart correspondence and drafts, 1985-2003; 2 (Box 5)
    - Agent Orange correspondence, lectures, and other materials, 1996-2005; 7 (Box 5)
    - Hastings Center, correspondence and other materials, 1998-1999 (Box 5)
    - Stem cell research, correspondence, notes, clippings and other materials, 2003-2006 (Box 5)
    - WNPR interview on Agent Orange, reference materials, 2002 (Box 5)
    - Princeton conference on bioethics schedule and clippings, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Westing Associates and Plant Resources Venture Funds publicity materials, Circa 1998-1995 (Box 5)
    - Ken Hartford Memorial Fund, correspondence and other materials, 1973-1991 (Box 5)
    - American Association of University Professors membership materials, 2001-2003 (Box 5)
    - American Association for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology membership materials, 1991-2007 (Box 5)
    - Plant Science Bulletin correspondence, 2001-2002 (Box 5)
    - Association for Practical and Professional Ethics membership materials, 1994-2006; 2 (Box 5)
    - Conference on Bioethics at Yale correspondence and other materials, 1985 (Box 5)
    - Trips to China, correspondence and typescript diary, 1971-1986; 2 (Box 5)
    - Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences membership materials, 1996-203 (Box 5)
    - Computer-related matters, correspondence, requisitions, and printed ephemera, 1994-2004 (Box 5)
    - Duke Ellington reminiscence and award materials, Circa 2002 (Box 5)
    - Yale School of Forestry and Environmental Studies correspondence and conference materials, 2000 (Box 5)
    - Frontier Research Program, Japan, correspondence, travel documents, and printed ephemera, 1987-1988 (Box 5)
    - Greenwich Continuing Education Lecture Series correspondence and related materials, 1990 (Box 5)
    - Henry Koerner Center for Emeritus Faculty correspondence and related materials, 2003-2005 (Box 5)
    - Nathan Mandell Memorial Fund correspondence, 1986-1990 (Box 5)
    - Patent application materials, 1986-1988 (Box 5)
    - Rice biotechnology symposium at Yale University, introductory remarks and related materials, 2003-2004 (Box 5)
    - Science and the Citizen lectures, publicity materials and correspondence, 1966-circa 1970; 2 (Box 5)
    - Swarthmore College honors examination, correspondence and related materials, 1956 (Box 5)
    - La Jolla Conference on Circadian Rhythms, conference materials and talks, 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - Vietnam talks, notes and related materials, 1972-1976 (Box 5)
    - Vietnam horticulture, articles, Circa 1971-1973 (Box 5)
    - U.S. Committee for Scientific Cooperation with Vietnam, 1984-1999; 3 (Box 5)
    - Vietnam, CSU professor slaying, clippings, 1984 (Box 6)
    - Vietnam U.S. Scientific Conference on Human Health and Environmental Effects of Agent Orange/Dioxins, correspondence, conference materials, and photographs, 1999-2003; 2 (Box 6)
    - Yale Vietnam Conference, conference materials, 2002 (Box 6)
    - Wayne Dwernychuk materials on Dioxin, offprints, 2002 (Box 6)